Finding Aid for William K. Frankena Papers 1927-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William K. Frankena papers
1927-1991
1961-1981
Frankena, William K.
Professor of philosophy at the University of Michigan, scholar and writer on moral philosophy, ethics, and philosophy of education. Collection includes philosophy papers written as a student at Calvin College, the University of Michigan, and Harvard; lecture notes and course materials, mainly from his teaching career at the University of Michigan; research articles and other manuscripts; formal lectures and conference papers; topical and background files on philosophy topics; correspondence; and files detailing University of Michigan departmental and committee responsibilities.
9538 Aa 2
14 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was received in October 1994 from Karl R. Frankena (donor 3157 ).
The collection is open for research.
William K. Frankena was born on June 21, 1908 in Manhattan, Montana. On June 23, 1934 he married Sadie Roelfs and they had two sons, Karl and Mark. William Frankena died on October 22, 1994 in Ypsilanti, Michigan. He had been a professor of philosophy at the University of Michigan for 41 years.
William Frankena began his higher education at Calvin College where he received an A.B. in 1930. Then Frankena received two M.A.'s, one from the University of Michigan in 1933 and the other from Harvard University in 1935. Frankena finished his dissertation titled "Recent Intuitionism in British Ethics" at Harvard in 1937 and received his Ph.D.
Frankena's teaching career began at the University of Michigan in 1937 where he started as an instructor of philosophy. In 1940 he became an assistant professor and in 1946 he was promoted to associate professor. In 1947, he was made full professor and appointed chairman of the Philosophy Department, a position he held until 1961. In 1978, he retired from the university. During his career, Frankena was a visiting lecturer and professor at Harvard, Columbia, Tokyo, University of Washington, and Princeton.
Frankena was a widely published philosopher. His research extended from the history of ethics to education and social philosophy. His most widely read book was Ethics (1963), which has 27 editions and is published in eight languages. He was the author of many other books such as Thinking about Morality (1980), Three Historical Philosophies of Education (1965), and Perspectives on Morality (1976) as well as the coauthor of many other books. He published journal articles in Mind, Philosophical Review, Philosophical Studies, Philosophy and Phenomenological Research, Journal of the History of Ideas, The Harvard Educational Review, and Review of Metaphysics.
He was a member of many university and professional committees as well as organizations. Committees with which Frankena was involved included the LSA Executive Committee for three terms, and the Qualifications Committee for Phi Beta Kappa for two terms. Frankena was a member of the American Philosophical Association, Phi Beta Kappa, the National Academy of Education and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He also served on the Board of Trustees at Chatham College for three terms, as the chairman on the Board of Officers for the American Philosophical Association for one term, the president of the Western Division of the American Philosophical Association, the chairman of the Council for Philosophical Studies for three terms, and as a Carus Lecturer for the American Philosophical Association.
The William Frankena papers document the development of a major philosopher and ethicist through his undergraduate and graduate school papers, published and unpublished articles, correspondence and curricular material. This collection (14 linear feet; 1927-1991) is organized into eight series which are based mainly upon the various professional activities of William Frankena. The series are: Undergraduate Studies, Graduate Studies, Teaching, Articles and Manuscripts, Lectures and Papers, Topical, Correspondence, and University of Michigan Activities.
Subjects:
Frankena, William K.; Ethical problems.; Ethics.; Ethicists.; Education--Philosophy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
- Undergraduate Studies, 1927-1930
  The Undergraduate Studies series (2 folders; 1927-1930) contains materials related to Frankena's undergraduate training at Calvin College. It is composed of papers which Frankena wrote as a student for various courses. They are arranged alphabetically.
  - Calvin College Papers, 1927-1930; 2 folders (Box 1)
- Graduate Studies, 1931-1937; 0.7 linear feet
  The Graduate Studies series (.7 linear feet; 1931-1937) includes papers at the University of Michigan and Harvard, along with various notes, rough drafts, and revisions of his dissertation. It is organized into two subseries: "Papers" and "Dissertation". The Papers subseries is arranged alphabetically by paper title. The Dissertation subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - Papers
    - "The Aesthetics of Immanuel Kant" (Phil. 201-University of Michigan) (Box 1)
    - "Alternative Systems," "Alternative Logics," "Foundational Codes" (Phil. 21-Harvard), 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Aristotle on Philosophy and Its Axioms" (Phil. 155-University of Michigan), 1931 (Box 1)
    - "Aristotle on Potentiality" (Harvard), 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Aspects and Logic," "Propositions and Proportional Functions," "Codification; Codes and Code-Forms" (Phil. 8-Harvard), 1934 (Box 1)
    - "Carneys Psychichalismus" (Psychology 5-Harvard), 1934 (Box 1)
    - "The Criterion of Truth in Immanuel Kant" (Phil. 201-University of Michigan) (Box 1)
    - "D. Hilbert and W. Ackermann Grundzuge der Theoretischen Logik (University of Michigan), 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Hegel's Political Philosophy" (University of Michigan), 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Intuitionism and Positivism" (Phil. 20-Harvard), 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Leibniz' Discourse on Metaphysics," "An Essay on Leibniz" (Phil. 14a-Harvard), 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - "Lyric Poetry and Man's Proposals" (Creative Writing-University of Michigan), 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - "Metaphysics and Ethics," "Rationalism and Causation" (Phil 20h-Harvard), 1934-1935 (Box 1)
    - "Plato's Theory of Knowledge" (Phil. 10-Harvard), 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - "The Poetry of Emily Dickinson" (Phil. 139-University of Michigan), 1931 (Box 1)
    - "The Prose of John Dryden" (English Prose-University of Michigan), 1930-1932 (Box 1)
    - "Psychology from the Standpoint of a Behaviorist" (Psychology 168-University of Michigan) (Box 1)
    - "Recent Intuitionism in British Ethics" (Phil. 20d-Harvard) (Box 1)
    - "The Romantic Conception of Pleasure" (English 166-University of Michigan), 1931 (Box 1)
    - "Royce's Philosophy of Religion" (University of Michigan), 1931 (Box 1)
    - "Self-Hood, An Essay in Metaphysics" (University of Michigan), 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Spinoza's Cogitate Metaphysics and Ethics Compared" (Phil. 14d-Harvard), 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - Submitted for the Hopwood Literary Contest (University of Michigan), 1931 (Box 1)
    - "The Theaetetus of Plato" (Phil. 154-University of Michigan), 1930-1931 (Box 1)
    - "The Timaeus of Plato," "A Study in Plato's Timaeus" (Phil. 3b-Harvard), 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - "What Think Ye of Substance" (University of Michigan), 1932 (Box 1)
  - Dissertation "Recent Intuitionism In British Ethics" (Harvard, 1937)
    - Manuscripts and Notes, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Revisions, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Teaching, 1937-1994; 4.3 linear feet
  The Teaching series (4.3 linear feet; 1937-1994) includes materials related to Frankena's teaching career as a professor of Philosophy at the University of Michigan, and as a visiting lecturer and professor at various other universities. It is composed of two subseries: "Lecture Notes" and "Course Materials". The Lecture Notes subseries (2 linear feet; 1956-1994) consists of dated, handwritten notes throughout his career. Since Frankena did not usually identify what class the lectures were for, these notes are arranged chronologically by year. The Course Materials subseries (2.3 linear feet; 1939-1976) includes materials such as course syllabi, reading lists, handouts of various types, examinations, and written notes by Frankena planning his courses. It is arranged alphabetically by course title and numerically by course number. The years in which the courses were offered are also included on the folder headings. If a course was not taught at the University of Michigan, this has also been noted on the folder heading.
  - Lecture Notes
    - 1956-1972, 17 folders (Box 2)
    - 1973-1994, 21 folders (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Examinations for the Ph.D (Box 3)
  - Course Material (Box 4)
    - Course Titles
      - Advanced Ethics (Phil. 218), 1939-1940 (Box 4)
      - American Ethics, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - American Philosophy (Phil. 110), 1950 (Box 4)
      - British Moralist (S 139-Columbia University), 1953 (Box 4)
      - Contemporary Philosophy (S 45 Columbia University and S 183 Harvard), 1953; 1955 (Box 4)
      - Course Evaluations (various years and classes) (Box 4)
      - Eighteenth Century British Moralist (Phil. 340), 1950-1951 (Box 4)
      - English and American Ethics (Phil. 130), 1948 (Box 4)
      - Ethics (Phil. 129), 1943 (Box 4)
      - Ethics (utilitarianism) (Box 4)
      - Ethics in America (Phil. 340), 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - Exercises in Elementary Logic (Phil. 33) (Box 4)
      - Great Books (Phil. 191 and 192), 1965-1967 (Box 4)
      - History of Ethics (Phil. 130), 1944-1945 (Box 4)
      - History of Ethics I (Phil. 130), 1942-1977; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - History of Ethics II (Christian Medieval), 1944-1973 (Box 4)
      - History of Ethics III (Phil. 130), 1949-1950; 1952-1961 (Box 4)
      - History of Ethics IV (Phil. 130), 1938-1939; 1941-1943 (Box 4)
      - History of Ethics V (Bentham, Mill, 19th and 20th century), 1943-1977 (Box 4)
      - Introduction to Analytical Philosophy of Education (Phil. 407), 1965 (Box 4)
      - Introduction to the University (University Course 101), 1975 (Box 4)
      - Medieval Philosophy (undated) (Box 4)
      - Modern Philosophy and Introduction to Philosophy, undated (Box 4)
      - Philosophy of Education (Phil. 407), 1959-1961 (Box 4)
      - Philosophy of Education (Phil. 407), 1963-1964 (Box 5)
      - Philosophy of Education (Phil. 407), 1968 (Box 5)
      - Philosophy of Education (Phil. 407), 1971-1974; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Philosophy of Education, undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Philosophy of Education (A 54, Harvard Graduate School of Education), 1962-1963 (Box 5)
      - Plato and the Stoics (Phil. 129), 1944 (Box 5)
      - Platonism (Phil. 34), 1950-1953 (Box 5)
      - Seminar in Current Philosophy (Phil. 311), 1952-1953 (Box 5)
      - Seminar on Problems in Recent Moral Philosophy (Phil. 268, Harvard), 1962 (Box 5)
      - Seventeenth Century Philosophy (Phil. 14, Harvard), 1941-1942 (Box 5)
      - Social Philosophy (Phil. 441), 1963-1964 (Box 5)
      - Topics in Philosophy (Phil. 129), 1943; 1945 (Box 5)
      - Value Theory and Aesthetics (Harvard and Radcliffe), 1941-1942 (Box 5)
    - Course Numbers
      - 33, circa 1940 (Box 5)
      - 34, 1940-1941; 1943-1948 (Box 5)
      - 37, 1944-1945; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 63, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
      - 98-99, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
      - 106, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
      - 130, 1945-1946; 1949-1950; 1953 (Box 5)
      - 142, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
      - 185, 1946-1948 (Box 5)
      - 198, 1944 (Box 5)
      - 200, 1943 (Box 6)
      - 200, 1945-1948; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 203, circa 1950; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 203, undated (Box 6)
      - 234, undated (Box 6)
      - 308, 1949-1950 (Box 6)
      - 340, 1954-1955 (Box 6)
      - 361, circa 1961-1973; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 407, 1967-1968 (Box 6)
      - 429, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - 429, 1974 (Box 6)
      - 436, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
      - 570, undated (Box 6)
      - 640, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
      - 640, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
      - 34, 134, 234, 1943-1976; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - 61, 261, 429, 1945-1966 (Box 6)
      - 129 and 142, 1943 (Box 6)
- Articles and Manuscripts, 1930-1990; 2.5 linear feet
  The Articles and Manuscripts series (2.5 linear feet; 1930-1990) consists of handwritten drafts or typed revisions of both published and unpublished articles and monographs composed by Frankena throughout his academic career. Since the dates were not available for all of them, it was only possible to arrange these materials alphabetically by the titles of the works. Dates are included on the folder heading when known.
  - The Ambivalence of Bernard Mandevill, by Hector Monro" (review), 1975 (Box 6)
  - "Beneficence in Ethics of Virtue,", 1981 (Box 6)
  - "Bentham and Mill on the Justification of the Principle of Utility,", 1982 (Box 6)
  - "Bird Watching Stories and Things,", undated (Box 6)
  - "Broad's Analysis of Ethical Terms,", undated (Box 6)
  - "Can Biology Help Ethics?", undated (Box 7)
  - "A Certain Kind of Commitment Word,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Classification of Volitional Expressions,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Cognitive and Non-Cognitive Aspects of Language,", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Concept of Morality,", 1966 (Box 7)
  - "The Concept of Education Today,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Concepts of Rational Action in the History of Ethics,", 1982 (Box 7)
  - "The Concept of Social Justice,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Concluding More or Less Philosophical Postscript" (for Goodpaster's volume), undated (Box 7)
  - "Draft of the Report of Curriculum Committee,", undated (Box 7)
  - Editions of Ethics (Box 7)
  - "Education" (for Dictionary of the History of Ideas), 1970 (Box 7)
  - "Education for the Good Life,", 1967 (Box 7)
  - "Educational Values and Goals: Some Dispositions to be Fastered,", 1966 (Box 7)
  - "Ethical Theory in America, 1930-1960,", undated (Box 7)
  - Ethics (Box 7)
  - "Ethics and the Environment,", 1977 (Box 7)
  - "The Ethics of Respect for Life,", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Ethics of Love Conceived as an Ethics of Virtue,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Ethics of Respect for Persons,", 1977; 1982 (Box 7)
  - " Ethics Revisited in 1979,", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Ethics of Right Reason,", 1981 (Box 7)
  - "An Ethics of Virtue,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Ewing's Case Against Naturalistic Theories of Value,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Four Theories of Types of Morality,", 1975 (Box 7)
  - "Freedom: Responsibility and Decision,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Frondizi on the Foundations of Moral Norms,", 1966 (Box 7)
  - "Geneva: The Speech-Act Analysis of Words,", undated (Box 7)
  - "Hare on the Levels of Moral Thinking,", 1984 (Box 7)
  - "Hare on Moral Weakness and the Definition of Morality,", 1984 (Box 7)
  - "Hutcheson's Moral Sense Theory,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Indefinability in Ethics,", 1936 (Box 8)
  - Introduction to an edition of Jonathan Edward's The Nature of True Virtue, 1960 (Box 8)
  - "Is Morality a Purely Personal Matter?", 1976 (Box 8)
  - "Is Morality Logically Dependent on Religion?", 1961 (Box 8)
  - "C.I. Lewis on the Ground and Nature of the Right,", 1964 (Box 8)
  - "Love and Principle in Christian Ethics,", undated (Box 8)
  - "MacIntyre and Modern Morality,", 1981 (Box 8)
  - "McCormick and the Traditional Distinction,", 1974 (Box 8)
  - "McMurrin and Smith on the Philosophy of Education,", 1962-1963 (Box 8)
  - "The Metaphysics of Value,", undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - "Methods of Ethics, 1977,", undated (Box 8)
  - "A Model for Analyzing a Philosophy of Education,", 1966 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Education, Moral Authority, and Moral Autonomy", circa 1973-1977 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Education: The Philosophical View,", 1968 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Philosophy and Moral Education,", undated (Box 8)
  - "(Moral) Philosophy and Moral Standards,", 1976 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Philosophy and World Hunger,", 1975 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Philosophy and the Future,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Moral Philosophy at Mid-Century,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Moral Philosophy in America,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Moral Philosophy in the United States Today,", 1964 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Principles as Principles for Institutions,", 1976 (Box 8)
  - "Moral Saints, Saints, and Moral Philosophy,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Morality and Conflict,", 1983 (Box 8)
  - "Morality and Religion, Relations of,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Must Morality Have an Object?", 1974 (Box 8)
  - "Natural and Inalienable Rights,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Newman, Religion, and the University,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Note A Self-Involving Utterance,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Notes on 'War and Morality',", 1968 (Box 8)
  - "The Object (Subject) of Moral Judgment,", 1973 (Box 8)
  - "Obligation and Ability,", undated (Box 8)
  - "Obligation and Motivation in Recent Moral Philosophy,", undated (Box 8)
  - "On Defining and Defending Natural Law,", undated (Box 8)
  - "On Defining Moral Judgments, Principles, and Codes,", 1973 (Box 8)
  - "On Distinguishing Critical and Positive Morality, Etc.", 1975 (Box 8)
  - "On Morality and Sex Change,", undated (Box 8)
  - "On the Hobby of Bird Watching,", undated (Box 8)
  - "On 'The Upside-down Curriculum',", undated (Box 8)
  - "Ought and Is Once More,", 1966 (Box 8)
  - "Our Belief in Reason,", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Pattern of Moral Philosophy in America", undated (Box 9)
  - "A Peculiar Set of Terms", undated (Box 9)
  - "Phi Beta Kappa: Guide of Life", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Philosopher's Attack on Morality", 1973 (Box 9)
  - "Philosophical Inquiry and the Schools", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Philosophy of Education", 1970 (Box 9)
  - "A Point of View for the Future", undated (Box 9)
  - "The Potential of Theology for Ethics", 1982-1983 (Box 9)
  - "Preface to Translation of Reiner's Book", undated (Box 9)
  - "Prichard and the Ethics of Virtue; Notes on a Footnote", 1969 (Box 9)
  - "The Principles of Morality", undated (Box 9)
  - "Recent Conceptions of Morality", undated (Box 9)
  - "Religion, Learning, and the University (Box 9)
  - "The Right to Life of Non-Human Beings,", 1981 (Box 9)
  - "Rights and Theories about Rights,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Sellers' Theory of Valuation,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Sidgwick and the History of Ethical Dualism,", 1988 (Box 9)
  - "Sidgwick's Methods of Ethics, EDT. 7, Page 1", circa 1988-1990 (Box 9)
  - "Sidney Hook, Pragmatism and the Magic Sense of Life,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Some Beliefs about Justice,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Spinoza's 'New Morality': Notes on Book IV,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Spinoza on the Knowledge of Good and Evil,", 1976 (Box 9)
  - "Theology Voluntarism Today,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Toward a Philosophy of Moral Education,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Toward a Policy for a Public Education,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Twentieth Century Philosophy Seen From the Middle,", 1950 (Box 9)
  - "Under What Net?", 1973 (Box 9)
  - "Value and Valuation,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Warnock Morality and Language,", undated (Box 9)
- Lectures and Papers, 1930-1987; 1.7 linear feet
  The Lectures and Papers series (1.7 linear feet; 1930-1987) includes handwritten and typed drafts of lectures delivered by Frankena in person, or which he submitted to various philosophical conferences, colloquia, symposia, or panel discussions. Dates were not available for all of this material, nor were the names of the conferences, symposia, etc. Thus it was only possible to arrange them alphabetically by title. Dates and/or conference names were included on the folder headings when available.
  - "The Basic Theory of Relevancy" (Institute on Advocacy, University of Michigan), 1956 (Box 9)
  - "The Bearing of Ethics on Morality" (Oxford), 1979 (Box 9)
  - "Benificence / Benevolence" (Conference on Private Philanthropy and the Public Good), 1985 (Box 9)
  - "Beyond Morality?" (Iowa Philosophy Society), 1976 (Box 9)
  - Boulder Summer Institute Lectures, 1966 (Box 9)
  - Carnegie Summer Institute in Philosophy Lectures (Notre Dame University), 1972 (Box 9)
  - "The Categorical Imperative" (Michigan State University), 1958 (Box 9)
  - "Comments on Mandelbaum,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Comments on Passmore,", undated (Box 9)
  - "Comments on Sturgeon on Brandt (and me),", 1981 (Box 9)
  - "The Concept of Education Today", circa 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - "The Concept of Morality" (Stockholm), 1965 (Box 9)
  - "Contra the Contras: A Trilogy,", 1987 (Box 9)
  - "Conversations with Carney and Hauerwas,", 1975 (Box 9)
  - "Discussion of John Dewey's 'Some Questions about Values',", undated (Box 9)
  - "Ethics in an Age of Science" (Princeton University), 1960 (Box 10)
  - "Ethics in British" (University of Wyoming), 1977 (Box 10)
  - "Ethics of Respect for Life" (Johns-Hopkins University), 1975 (Box 10)
  - "Sidgwick's Methods of Ethics, EDT. 7, Page 1", circa 1988-1990 (Box 10)
  - "The Foundations of Normative Ethics,", 1964-1965 (Box 10)
  - "Four Theories of Types of Morality,", undated (Box 10)
  - "Freedom: Responsibility and Decision" (Vienna Congress of Philosophy), 1968 (Box 10)
  - "G.H. Von Wright on the Nature of Morality,", 1974 (Box 10)
  - Hare, undated (Box 10)
  - "Has Morality an Independent Bottom?", undated (Box 10)
  - "Is There a Third Kind of Knowledge?", undated (Box 10)
  - "Is Hobbes a Little Liberal or a Little Conservative?" (Hobbes Conference, University of Michigan), 1987 (Box 10)
  - "Is Morality A System of Ordinary Oughts?", undated (Box 10)
  - "Is the Philosophy of Education Intellectually Responsible?" (Philosophy of Education Society Meeting, Detroit), 1961 (Box 10)
  - "Justice, Social and Global" (Stockholm Symposium on Social Justice), 1978 (Box 10)
  - "Justification in Ethics and 'The Moral Point of View'" (Yale Lectures), 1957 (Box 10)
  - "John Hooker on Moral Sense Theories,", 1977 (Box 10)
  - "Kantian Ethics Today" (Hope College), 1985 (Box 10)
  - "Methods in 19th Century Ethics" (Gormell College), 1976 (Box 10)
  - "Major Moral Perspectives" (Haverford Institute Lectures), 1974 (Box 10)
  - "Methods of Ethics,", 1977 (Box 10)
  - "Moral Decency" (University of Texas at Dallas Lecture), 1984 (Box 10)
  - "Morality and Moral Education,", undated (Box 10)
  - "Moral Person and Moral Society" (St. Mary's College), 1981 (Box 10)
  - "Moral Point of View Theories" (Delaware Lecture), 1979 (Box 10)
  - "Must Morality Have an Object?", undated (Box 10)
  - "The Nature of Morality" (Carus Lectures), 1973-1974 (Box 10)
  - "The New Morality: Situational Ethics" (University of Redlands), 1969 (Box 10)
  - "On A Certain Kind of Self-Committing Expression" (Student-Faculty Lecture), 1977 (Box 10)
  - "On 'Is The History of Ethics an Outlying Province of Philosophy'?", 1978 (Box 10)
  - "On Saying the Ethical Thing,", 1966 (Box 10)
  - "On Schneewind's 'The Misfortunes of Virtue'" (University of Michigan Colloquium in Philosophy), 1984 (Box 10)
  - "On the Cognitive Non Cognitive Distinction" (Lund University), 1965 (Box 10)
  - "The Philosopher's Attack on Morality" (London), 1973 (Box 10)
  - "The Philosophy of Vocation,", undated (Box 10)
  - "Prichard and the Ethics of Virtue" (Moorhead), 1969 (Box 10)
  - "The Principles of Morality,", 1966-1967 (Box 10)
  - "Public Education and the Good Life" (Penn State University), 1958 (Box 10)
  - "Recent Epistemology and the Planning of a Collage Curriculum" (Macalester College), 1964 (Box 10)
  - "Religion, Learning, and the University" (Notre Dame), 1959 (Box 10)
  - "Respect for Persons, Etc." (Davidson College), 1977 (Box 10)
  - "Rights and Theories about Rights" (Hope College), 1985 (Box 10)
  - "Shklar on Legal, Moral, and Political Decisionism,", undated (Box 10)
  - "Situational Ethics" (Cornell), 1969 (Box 10)
  - "Some Questions about Morality,", 1965 (Box 10)
  - "Some Beliefs about Justice" (Lindley Lecture, University of Kansas), 1966 (Box 10)